I have one more reason for optimism:
لدي سبب إضافي للتفاؤل:
climate change.
التغير المناخي.
Maybe you don't believe it, but here is the fact.
قد لا تؤمنون بذلك. ولكن ها هي الحقيقة
On December 12, 2015,
في 12 ديسمبر 2015،
in Paris, under the United Nations,
في باريس و برعاية الأمم المتحدة،
195 governments got together
اجتمعت 195 حكومة
and unanimously --
و بالإجماع --
if you've worked with governments, you know how difficult that is --
وإذا كنتم قد عملتم مع الحكومات ستعرفون كم يكون ذلك صعبا --
unanimously decided
و قرروا بالإجماع
to intentionally change the course of the global economy
العمل بجدية على تغيير اتجاه الاقتصاد العالمي
in order to protect the most vulnerable
لغرض حماية الأكثر ضعفا
and improve the life of all of us.
و تحسين حياتنا جميعا.
Now, that is a remarkable achievement.
حسنا، هذا إنجاز رائع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But it is even more remarkable
و لكن الأكثر لفتا للنظرهو
if you consider where we had been just a few years ago.
لو تصورت أين كنا قبل بضع سنوات فقط.
2009, Copenhagen.
كوبنهاغن 2009.
Who remembers Copenhagen?
من يتذكر كوبنهاغن؟
Well, after years of working toward a climate agreement,
بعد سنوات من العمل نحو إتفاقية للمناخ،
the same governments convened in Copenhagen
إجتمعت نفس الحكومات في كوبنهاغن
and failed miserably.
وفشلت فشلا ذريعا.
Why did it fail miserably?
لماذا فشلت فشلا ذريعا؟
For many different reasons,
لأسباب عديدة مختلفة،
but primarily because of the deeply entrenched divide
ولكن أساسا بسبب التقسيم العميق الراسخ
between the global North and the global South.
بين عالم الشمال و عالم الجنوب.
So now, six months after this failure,
والآن و بعد ستة أشهر من هذا الفشل،
I was called in to assume the responsibility
تمت دعوتي لاستلام المسؤولية
of the global climate change negotiations.
في مفاوضات التغير المناخي العالمي.
You can imagine, the perfect moment to start this new job.
ولكم أن تتصوروا، اللحظة المناسبة للبدء بهذه الوظيفة.
The global mood on climate change was in the trash can.
كان المزاج العام نحو التغير المناخي في سلة النفايات.
No one believed
لم يؤمن أحد
that a global agreement could ever be possible.
بإمكانية التوصل لاتفاقية عالمية.
In fact, neither did I.
و في الواقع حتى أنا لم أؤمن.
If you promise not to tell anyone outside of this wonderful TED audience,
إذا وعدتم بأن لا تخبروا أحدا خارج هذا الجمهور الرائع المجتمع هنا،
I'm going to divulge a secret
فسأكشف لكم سرا
that has been gratefully buried by history.
تم دفنه تاريخيا بشكل مدهش.
On my first press conference,
في أول مؤتمر صحفي لي،
a journalist asked, "Um, Ms. Figueres,
سألني أحد الصحفيين، "السيدة غريفس،
do you think that a global agreement is ever going to be possible?"
هل تعتقدين بإمكانية تحقق اتفاقية عالمية ؟"
And without engaging brain, I heard me utter,
و بدون تفكير، سمعت نفسي أقول،
"Not in my lifetime."
"لم أتخيل ذلك في حياتي."
Well, you can imagine the faces of my press team
حسنا، لكم أن تتصوروا وجوه فريقي الإعلامي
who were horrified at this crazy Costa Rican woman
الذين فزعوا من هذه المرأة المجنونة القادمة من كوستاريكا
who was their new boss.
التي كانت رئيستهم الجديدة.
And I was horrified, too.
و حتى أنا فزعت، أيضا.
Now, I wasn't horrified at me, because I'm kind of used to myself.
والآن أنا لم أفزع من نفسي لأنني نوعا ما متعودة على نفسي
I was actually horrified
أنا في الواقع فزعت
at the consequences of what I had just said,
على ما يترتب على ما قلته للتو،
at the consequences for the world
على نتائجه على العالم
in which all our children are going to have to live.
الذي سيكون على كل أطفالنا الحياة فيه.
It was frankly a horrible moment for me,
و بصراحة كانت لحظة فظيعة بالنسبة لي،
and I thought, well, no, hang on,
و فكرت، حسنا، لا، تماسكي،
hang on.
تماسكي.
Impossible is not a fact,
المستحيل ليس حقيقة،
it's an attitude.
إنه موقف.
It's only an attitude.
إنه فقط موقف.
And I decided right then and there that I was going to change my attitude
وقررت عند ذاك و وقتها بأنني سأغير موقفي
and I was going to help the world change its attitude on climate change.
و أن أساعد العالم لتغيير موقفه من التغيير المناخي.
So I don't know --
لذا أنا لا أعرف --
No, just this? Thanks.
كلا، هذا فقط؟ شكرا.
I don't know --
لا أعرف--
what you would do
ماذا ستفعلون
if you were told your job is to save the planet.
إذا أخبركم أحد إن واجبك هو إنقاذ الكوكب.
Put that on the job description.
ضع ذلك على الوصف الوظيفي
And you have full responsibility,
و تكون عليك كل المسؤولية،
but you have absolutely no authority,
و لكن ليس لديك أي سلطة على الإطلاق،
because governments are sovereign in every decision that they take.
لأن الحكومات ذوات سيادة في كل قراراتها التي تتخذها.
Well, I would really love to know
حسنا، أنا أود فعلا أن أعرف
what you would do on the first Monday morning,
ماذا ستفعل في أول صباح ليوم الاثنين،
but here's what I did: I panicked.
و لكن هاكم ما فعلته أنا: لقد ذعرت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then I panicked again,
ثم ذعرت ثانية،
because I realized I have no idea how we're going to solve this problem.
لأنني عرفت بأنه ليست لدي أي فكرة عن كيفية حل هذه المشكلة.
And then I realized I have no idea how we're going to solve this problem,
ثم عرفت بأنه ليست لدي أي فكرة عن كيفية حل هذه المشكلة،
but I do know one thing:
و لكني أعرف شيئا واحدا:
we have got to change the tone of this conversation.
أن علينا أن نغير نبرة هذا الحديث.
Because there is no way you can deliver victory
لأنك لا تستطيع أن تقدم هذا النصر بأي طريقة
without optimism.
دون التفاؤل.
And here,
و هنا،
I use optimism as a very simple word,
فإنني أستخدم التفاؤل ككلمة بسيطة
but let's understand it in its broader sense.
ولكن دعنا نفهمها بمعناها الواسع
Let's understand it as courage,
لنفهمها باعتبارها الشجاعة،
hope, trust, solidarity,
و الأمل والثقة و التضامن،
the fundamental belief that we humans can come together
والتفكير الأساسي بأننا نحن البشر قادرون على أن نكون معا
and can help each other to better the fate of mankind.
و نستطيع مساعدة بعضنا البعض لتحسين مصير البشرية.
Well, you can imagine that I thought that without that,
حسنا، تستطيعون تخيل إنني فكرت كذلك دون هذا،
there was no way we were going to get out of the paralysis of Copenhagen.
لم يكن هناك من سبيل للخروج من عقدة كوبنهاغن.
And for six years,
و لست سنوات،
I have stubbornly, relentlessly injected optimism into the system,
كنت أحقن النظام بالتفاؤل بإصرار و بلا هوادة،
no matter what the questions from the press --
مهما كانت الأسئلة من الصحافة --
and I have gotten better at those --
و أصبحت أحسن أمام هؤلاء --
and no matter what the evidence to the contrary.
و مهما كانت الدلائل عكس ذلك.
And believe you me, there has been a lot of contrary evidence.
و صدقوني، فقد كان هناك كثير من الدلائل عكس ذلك.
But relentless optimism into the system.
و لكن استمر بحقن التفاؤل بلا هوادة في النظام.
And pretty soon,
و بعد فترة قليلة،
we began to see changes happening in many areas,
بدأنا برؤية حدوث التغيرات في مختلف الحقول،
precipitated by thousands of people,
تترسخ لدى الآلاف من الناس،
including many of you here today,
و بضمنهم كثير من الموجودين هنا اليوم،
and I thank you.
و أنا اشكركم.
And this TED community will not be surprised
ولن يتفاجأ مجتمع TED هذا
if I tell you the first area
لو أخبرتكم أن المجال الأول
in which we saw remarkable change
الذي لمسنا فيه تغييرا بارزا
was ...
كان ...
technology.
التكنولوجيا.
We began to see that clean technologies,
لقد بدأنا نرى التكنولوجيات النظيفة،
in particular renewable energy technologies,
و خاصة تكنولوجيا الطاقة المتجددة،
began to drop price and increase in capacity,
التي بدأت أسعارها بالانخفاض و سعاتها في الازدياد،
to the point where today we are already building
إلى درجة إننا نبني اليوم
concentrated solar power plants
مشاريع طاقة شمسية مركزة
that have the capacity to power entire cities,
لها سعات تكفي لتزويد مدن كاملة بالطاقة،
to say nothing of the fact of what we are doing on mobility
ناهيكم عن حقيقة أننا نعمل على الحركة
and intelligent buildings.
و المباني الذكية.
And with this shift in technologies,
و مع التغير في التكنولوجيا،
we were able to begin to understand
تمكنا من البدء بفهم
that there was a shift in the economic equation,
أن هناك تغيرا في المعادلة الاقتصادية،
because we were able to recognize
لأننا تمكنا من تمييز
that yes, there are huge costs to climate change,
أن هناك كلفة عالية للتغير المناخي،
and yes, there are compounded risks.
نعم، وأن هناك مخاطر مضافة.
But there also are economic advantages
و لكن هناك أيضا منافع اقتصادية
and intrinsic benefits,
و فوائد اساسية،
because the dissemination of the clean technologies
لأن نشر التكنولوجيا النظيفة
is going to bring us cleaner air,
سيجلب لنا هواء أنظف،
better health,
و صحة أحسن،
better transportation, more livable cities,
و نقلا أفضل و مدنا أصلح للعيش
more energy security,
و أمانا أكثر للطاقة،
more energy access to the developing world.
وتسهيلا أكثر لوصول الطاقة إلى العالم النامي.
In sum, a better world than what we have now.
و في المجموع، الحصول على عالم أفضل مما لدينا الآن.
And with that understanding,
و بهذا الفهم،
you should have witnessed, in fact, part of you were,
ولا بد إنكم قد شهدتم، أو بعضكم،
the spread of ingenuity and excitement
إنتشار الإبداع والحماس
that went through, first through nonnational governments,
الذي سار قدما، أولا في الحكومات غير الوطنية،
the private sector, captains of industry, insurance companies,
و في القطاع الخاص، و قيادات الصناعة، و شركات التأمين،
investors, city leaders, faith communities,
و المستثمرين و قادة المدن و المجتمعات المؤمنة،
because they all began to understand, this actually can be in their interest.
لأنهم جميعا بدأوا بفهم إن هذا يمكن أن يكون فعلا لمصلحتهم.
This can actually improve their bottom line.
وإن هذا قادر على أن يرفع حدودهم الدنيا فعلا.
And it wasn't just the usual suspects.
و لم تكن هناك الشكوك الاعتيادية فقط.
I have to tell you I had the CEO of a major, major oil and gas company
و أود أن أخبركم أن رئيس إحدى شركات النفط والغاز الكبيرة جدا جدا
come to me at the beginning of last year
زارني بداية العام الماضي
and say --
و قال --
privately, of course --
بشكل خصوصي طبعا --
he did not know how he was going to change his company,
إنه لا يعرف كيف سيقوم بتغيير شركته،
but he is going to change it,
و لكنه سيغيرها،
because he's interested in long-term viability.
لأنه مهتم في جدواها على المدى البعيد.
Well, now we have a shift in the economic equation,
حسنا، أصبح الآن لدينا تغيير في المعادلة الأقتصادية،
and with that, with broader support from everyone,
و بذلك، و مع الدعم الواسع من الجميع،
it did not take very long before we saw that national governments
لم يأخذ الأمر طويلا قبل أن نرى الحكومات الوطنية
woke up to the fact that this is in their national interest.
تستيقظ على حقيقة أن هذا سيصب في مصلحتهم الوطنية.
And when we asked countries to begin to identify
و عندما طلبنا من البلدان أن تبدأ في تحديد
how they could contribute to global efforts
كيفية مشاركتهم في الجهود العالمية
but based on their national interest,
ولكن بناءا على مصالحهم الوطنية،
189 countries out of 195,
فإن 189 بلدا من 195 بلدا،
189 countries sent their comprehensive climate change plans,
189 بلدا أرسلوا خططهم الشاملة للتغيير البيئي
based on their national interest,
المبنية على مصالحهم الوطنية،
concurrent with their priorities,
متزامنة مع أولوياتهم،
consistent with their national sustainable development plans.
الموافقة لخططهم الوطنية للتنمية المستدامة.
Well,
حسنا،
once you protect the core interests of nations,
ما أن تبدأ بحماية المصالح المركزية للأمم،
then you can understand that nations were ready
حتى يمكنك تفهم أن الأمم جاهزة
to begin to converge onto a common path,
لتبدأ باللقاء في طريق مشترك
onto a common direction of travel
في التحرك نحو اتجاه مشترك
that is going to take us probably several decades,
من الممكن أن يأخذنا عدة عقود،
but over those several decades is going to take us
ولكن من خلال هذا العدد من العقود ، سيأخذنا
into the new economy,
إلى الاقتصاد الجديد،
into a decarbonized, highly resilient economy,
إقتصاد مرن جدا و خال من الكربون.
And the national contributions that are currently on the table
و ستكون المشاركات الوطنية التي على الطاولة
on behalf of national governments
من الحكومات الوطنية
are insufficient to get us to a stabilized climate,
غير كافية لتوصلنا إلى مناخ مستقر،
but they are only the first step,
ولكنها الخطوة الأولى فقط،
and they will improve over time.
و لكنها ستتحسن مع الوقت،
And the measurement, reporting and verification of all of those efforts
و ستكون القياسات و التقارير و تدقيقها، لكل هذه الجهود
is legally binding.
ملزمة قانونا.
And the checkpoints that we're going to have every five years
و ستكون نقاط التفتيش التي سنقوم بها كل خمس سنوات
to assess collective progress towards our goal are legally binding,
لتقييم التقدم المشترك نحو الهدف ستكون ملزمة قانونا.
and the path itself toward a decarbonized and more resilient economy
والطريق نفسه نحو اقتصاد مرن أكثر و خال من الكربون
is legally binding.
سيكون ملزما قانونا.
And here's the more important part:
و هنا يأتي الجزء الأهم:
What did we have before?
ماذا كان لدينا سابقا؟
A very small handful of countries
عدد صغير جدا من البلدان
who had undertaken very reduced,
التي أخذت على عاتقها التزامات مختصرة
short-term emission reduction commitments
و قصيرة المدى لتقليص الانبعاثات
that were completely insufficient
والتي كانت تماما غير كافية
and furthermore, largely perceived as a burden.
والتي كانت تمثل عائقا بشكل كبير.
Now what do we have?
والآن ماذا لدينا؟
Now we have all countries of the world contributing with different intensities
الآن لدينا جميع دول العالم تشارك بكميات مختلفة
from different approaches in different sectors,
من مختلف الطرق و في مجالات مختلفة،
but all of them contributing to a common goal
لكنها جميعا تشترك في هدف واحد
and along a path
و على طريق
with environmental integrity.
خدمة سلامة البيئة.
Well, once you have all of this in place
و الآن، ما أن تجمع كل شيء في مكانه
and you have shifted this understanding,
و أن تنقل هذا الفهم،
then you see that governments were able to go to Paris
عندئذ سترى إن جميع الحكومات ستكون قادرة على الذهاب إلى باريس
and adopt the Paris agreement.
و تبني إتفاقية باريس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So,
و عليه،
as I look back
عندما أنظر إلى الخلف
over the past six years,
على مدى الست سنوات،
first I remember
أتذكر أولا
the day the Paris agreement was adopted.
اليوم الذي تم تبني قمة باريس فيه.
I cannot tell you the euphoria in the room.
لا أستطيع أن أخبركم عن الفرحة التي عمت القاعة.
5,000 people jumping out of their seats,
5000 شخص يقفزون في مقاعدهم،
crying, clapping, screaming, yelling,
يبكون ويصفقون و يصرخون و يزعقون،
torn between euphoria and still disbelief at what they had just seen,
مشتتين بين الفرح و عدم تصديق ما رأوه حينذاك،
because so many people
لأن هذا العدد الكبير من الناس
had worked for years towards this, and this was finally their reality.
غملوا لعدة سنوات نحو هذا و أصبح هذا أخيرا حقيقة واقعة.
And it wasn't just those who had participated directly.
و لم يكن هؤلاء فقط الذين ساهموا مباشرة.
A few weeks ago, I was with a colleague
قبل بضعة اسابيع، كنت مع أحد زملائي
who was trying to decide
الذي كان يحاول أن يقرر
on a Tahitian pearl that he wanted to give to his wonderful wife Natasha.
أي لؤلؤة من تاهيتي يريد أن يهديها لزوجته الرائعة ناتاشا.
And once he had finally decided what he was going to buy,
و ما أن قرر أخيرا ما سيشتري،
the jeweler said to him,
قال الجواهرجي له:
"You know, you're very lucky that you're buying this now,
" أتعرف إنك محظوظ جدا لأنك تشتري هذه الآن،
because these pearls could go extinct very soon because of climate change."
لأن هذه اللآلئ يمكن أن تنقرض تماما بسبب التغيير المناخي."
"But," the jeweler said, "have you heard,
وأضاف الجواهرجي" ولكن هل سمعت،
the governments have just come to a decision,
بأن الحكومات توصلت إلى قرار،
and Tahiti could have a chance."
و إن تاهيتي قد تكون لها فرصة."
Well, what a fantastic confirmation
حسنا، ما أروع هذا التأكيد
that perhaps, perhaps here is hope,
بأنه يمكن، نعم يمكن أن يكون هناك أمل،
here is a possible chance.
هناك فرصة ممكنة.
I'm the first one to recognize that we have a lot of work still to do.
أنا أول من يعرف إنه لا يزال علينا الكثير من العمل نقوم به،
We've only just started our work on climate change.
لقد بدأنا العمل توا على التغيير المناخي.
And in fact, we need to make sure that we redouble our efforts
و في الواقع، نحن نحتاج للتأكد من أننا سنضاعف جهودنا
over the next five years that are the urgent five years.
خلال السنوات الخمس القادمة.
But I do believe
و لكني أؤمن
that we have come over the past six years
بأننا تجاوزنا خلال السنوات الست الماضية
from the impossible
مرحلة المستحيل
to the now unstoppable.
إلى مرحلة الانطلاق.
And how did we do that? By injecting transformational optimism
كيف قمنا بذلك؟ بواسطة حقن التفاؤل التحولي
that allowed us to go from confrontation to collaboration,
الذي سمح لنا بالتحول من المواجهة إلى التعاون،
that allowed us to understand that national and local interests
الذي سمح لنا بفهم أن المصالح الوطنية و المحلية
are not necessarily at odds with global needs,
ليستا بالضرورة متعارضتين مع حاجات العالم،
and that if we understand that, we can bring them together
و إننا لو فهمنا ذلك ، يمكن أن نضعهما معا
and we can merge them harmoniously.
و يمكن أن ندمجهما معا بشكل متناغم.
And as I look forward to other global issues
و عندما أنظر للمواضيع الدولية الأخرى
that will require our attention this century --
التي تتطلب اهتمامنا هذا القرن --
food security, water security, home security, forced migration --
الأمن الغذائي، الأمان المائي، الأمن الوطني، الهجرة الإجبارية --
I see that we certainly do not know
أرى إننا بالتأكيد لا نعرف
how we are going to solve those problems yet.
كيف سنعالج كل هذه المشاكل حتى الآن.
But we can take a page out of what we have done on climate change
و لكننا يمكن أن نأخذ صفحة مما فعلناه للتغير المناخي
and we can understand
و يمكننا أن نفهم
that we have got to reinterpret the zero-sum mentality.
أن علينا إعادة تفسير عقلية التعادل.
Because we were trained to believe that there always are winners and losers,
لأننا تدربنا على الإيمان بأن هناك دائما رابحون و خاسرون.
and that your loss is my gain.
وأن خسارتك تعني ربحي.
Well, now that we're in a world
حسنا، و بما أننا في عالم
in which we have reached planetary boundaries
وصلنا فيه إلى حدود الكواكب
and that we are not just so interconnected,
وبأننا لسنا فقط مترابطين
but increasingly interdependent on each other,
بل معتمدين على بعضنا بشكل متزايد،
your loss is no longer my gain.
فإن خسارتك لا تعني بعد الآن ربحا لي.
We're either all losers
نحن جميعا إما أن نكون خاسرين
or we all can be winners.
أو يمكننا أن نكون رابحين جميعا.
But we are going to have to decide
و لكن علينا اتخاذ القرار
between zero and sum.
بين الصفر و المجموع.
We're going to have to decide between zero benefit for all
علينا أن نقرر بين اللافائدة المطلقة بالنسبة لن جميعا
or living life as the sum of all of us.
أو العيش في حياة كنتيجة لنا جميعا.
We've done it once. We can do it again.
لقد فعلناها مرة. و نحن قادرون على فعلها ثانية.
Thanks.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)